Before we get started into real physics, I
would
like to review some basic concepts that
are
really helpful to know in order to do
physics
well. First of all, we would go over
vectors
and scalars. So what are vectors and
scalars?
Vectors and scalars are considered
physical
quantities. And that means that they
describe
measurable quantities of the physical
world.
For example, speed or distance.
And these physical quantities fall into
two
different sections, vectors and scalars.
What's the difference? First of all,
scalars.
A scalar is a quantity that is completely
described
by magnitude only. So it has a size, but
there
is no direction associated with it.
On the other hand, vectors have both a
magnitude
and a direction. An example of the
difference
between these two is scalars could be
distance,
while vectors, an example, would be
displacement.
Now, what's the difference between
distance
and displacement? Let's say we want to get
from
point A to point B on a map.
The distance travelled is, let's say you
took
a curvy trail. The distance travelled will
be
your total distance travelled.
If you were to take the trail and you were
to
start a GPS or a workout timer, that would
be
your distance. However, your displacement
only
takes into account the starting point and
the
ending point because it has to have a
direction.
So the displacement doesn't matter how,
what
trail you took. The displacement is just
the
distance, the closest distance between A
and
B. So distance could, you could go
anywhere
and it would vary. But if you start from
this
point and end at that point, the
displacement
is always the same. Another example of a
scalar
versus quantity would be speed. Speed is a
quantity, while velocity is a vector.
This is because velocity has a direction.
For
example, if you have a car going to the
right
at 3 metres per second, then its speed
would
be equal to 3 metres per second.
However, its velocity must have a
direction.
Since it's a vector, you would say 3
metres
per second to the right. And directions
are
usually depicted by square brackets, like
over
here. Another really useful thing to know,
and
it also appears a lot in IB Math as well,
is
compasses. Compasses are used to depict
direction.
For example, this would be north, east,
south,
west. There are two types of things you
can
do for compasses. Bearings and normal
direction.
Bearings are angles relative to the north
axis.
So for example, if a car had a velocity of
metres per second with an angle of let's
say
30 degrees, the bearing would be relative
to
north. So the bearing would be like this.
And that would be 120 degrees.
That would be the bearing. However, normal
direction
is when you actually state the axis.
So same example over here. If a car was
going
3 metres per second over here and this was
degrees, well you know that this is east
and
then this is south. So since it's 30
degrees
to the east, you would say that it's going
metres per second east 30 degrees south.
So 30 degrees is relative to the east axis
and
it's facing the south direction as well.
And usually in physics, we use normal
direction
over bearings. Bearings is more of math.
That's it for the first video.
Basically, it's just a simple example.
This
is a starter to get you familiar with
vectors
and scalars and how to answer your
questions
in physics. Thank you for watching and I
hope
you enjoyed.